<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

  File:   introduction.xml
  Author: Greg Wilson, Alex Samuel
  Date:   2000-11-07

  Contents:
    Chapter `Introduction' of qmtrack design document.

  This is part of the master document contained in qmtrack.xml.

  Copyright (C) 2000 CodeSourcery LLC.  This material may
  be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions set forth in
  the Software Carpentry Open Publication License, which is available at:

    http://www.software-carpentry.com/openpub-license.html

-->
<chapter id="chap-introduction">
 <title id="chap-introduction-title">Introduction</title>

 <para>This document outlines the design of &qmtrack;, an
 Internet-enabled issue-tracking system which will manage a number of
 issues (with properties such as "description", "priority", and so on)
 and provide the ability to
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>submit new issues,</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>find and edit existing issues, and</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>discuss issues with other participants.</para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 The system will facilitate communication among the participants by
 managing discussions and notifying interested parties when issues are
 edited.</para>

 <para>This design draws on experience from an existing issue-tracking
 system called <ulink
 url="http://www.software-carpentry.com/entries/second-round/track/Roundup/">
 Roundup</ulink>, and from the ideas discussed in Udell's <ulink
 url="http://www.software-carpentry.com/Groupware/report.html"><citetitle
 pubwork="article">Internet Groupware for Scientific
 Collaboration</citetitle></ulink>.</para>

 <para>This document incorporates material written by Ka-Ping Yee in
 his <ulink
 url="http://www.software-carpentry.com/entries/track/Roundup/Roundup.html">first
 round</ulink> and <ulink
 url="http://www.software-carpentry.com/entries/second-round/track/Roundup/">second
 round</ulink> proposals to the &sc; project design
 competitions.</para>

 <section id="sec-background">
  <title id="sec-background-title">Background</title>

  <para>A typical software project requires the management of many
  tasks, usually distributed among several collaborators.  In fact,
  any project team could use a tool for sorting out and discussing all
  the relevant issues.  A common approach is to set up some kind of
  "to-do" list that people can share.</para>

  <para>However, to address the overall problem we need much more than
  just a shared to-do list; we need to manage a growing body of
  knowledge and experience to help a team collaborate effectively on a
  project.  If this is done well, an issue-tracking system can be a
  collective memory for a development team, as well as a powerful
  workflow management tool.</para>

  <para>In order to achieve this, a good issue-tracking system should
  have at least the following properties:
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para><emphasis>Low barrier to participation.</emphasis> The
     usefulness of the tool depends entirely on the information people
     contribute to it.  It must be made as easy as possible to submit
     new issues and contribute information about existing
     issues.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para><emphasis>Straightforward navigation.</emphasis> It should
     be easy for users to extract information they need from the
     system to direct their decisions and tasks.  They should be able
     to get a decent overview of things as well as finding specific
     information when they know what they're after.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para><emphasis>Controlled information flow.</emphasis> The users
     must have control over how much information and what information
     they get.  A common flaw of some issue-tracking systems is that
     they inundate users with so much useless e-mail that people avoid
     the system altogether.</para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </para>

 </section>

 <section id="sec-ui-intro">
  <title id="sec-ui-intro-title">User Interface</title>

  <para>The effective power of many systems is diminished or negated
  by hard-to-use interfaces.  If it is tedious or difficult to enter,
  search for, or summarize information, users will do it as little as
  possible, which in turn reduces the payback for using the
  system.</para>

  <para>In order to avoid this vicious circle, &qmtrack; must give
  users access through three modes of interaction: command-line,
  e-mail, and web browsers.  (A fourth method, via scripts, is
  possible by using the internal &api;s of the &qmtrack; system.)  We
  see e-mail and web browsers as the most important, both because we
  envisage &qmtrack; being used in widely-distributed environments,
  and because they are the most constraining of the five modes.</para>

  <para>E-mail is best suited for the submission of new items since
  most people are most comfortable with composing long messages in
  their own favourite e-mail client. E-mail also permits them to
  mention URLs or attach files relevant to their submission.  Indeed,
  in many cases people are already used to making requests by sending
  e-mail to a mailing list of people; they can do exactly the same
  thing to use Roundup without even thinking about it. Similarly,
  people are already familiar with holding discussions in e-mail, and
  plenty of valuable usage conventions and software tools already
  exist for that medium.</para>

  <para>Web browsers, on the other hand, are best suited for
  summarizing and seeking information, because they can present an
  interactive overview of items.  Since the Web has forms, it's also
  the best place to edit items.</para>

  <section>
   <title>Editing</title>

   <para>Since &qmtrack; is intended to support arbitrary user-defined
   item properties, the item editing interface must be automatically
   generated from those properties.  As with most configurable
   systems, &qmtrack; will therefore include a small set of base types
   (such as integer, string, date, and so on), and allow users to
   specialize or combine these to create richer types.  The specifics
   of these types are discussed in <link linkend="sec-fields"
   endterm="sec-fields-title"></link>.</para>

   <para>The configuration for &qmtrack; will include a template
   describing how to lay out the web pages used to interact with the
   &qmtrack; database.  &qmtrack; automatically generates web forms
   suitable for read-only display, editing, and querying of issues.
   Each type has its own appropriate editing widget.  For example,
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>String properties appear as text fields.</para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>Date properties appear as text fields.</para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>Choice (enumerated) properties appear as selection
      lists.</para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
   Additional hints may be specified to tune the user interface
   further.  For instance, a text field may be specified as
   single-line or multi-line; the appropriate text fields are used
   automatically for this field.</para>

  </section>

  <section>
   <title>Browsing and Searching</title>

   <para>The database of issues can grow quite large and complex in
   many deployments, and sophisticated tools for querying the database
   are important.  Issues may be selected using expressions from a
   restricted subset of Python.  Fields in each issue are referred to
   as if they are variables, and each issue is considered to match if
   the expression would evaluate to a true boolean value.  Python's
   expression syntax is sufficiently straightforward and similar to
   plain English that the query syntax will be quite easy to master
   even for those without previous Python experience.  The query
   syntax will be available </para>

   <para>Searching the issue database via the web interface should be
   as much like browsing as possible.  The user should simply be able
   to click on things that seem interesting, and the information
   should narrow down comfortably until the goal is in sight.
   Experience shows that while one-shot searches may be appropriate
   when users are looking for specific items, and know exactly what
   they want, it's not very helpful when users want an overview ("Are
   there more high-priority items than there were last week?"), are
   trying to do comparisons ("I have some time this week, so who is
   busiest and could most use some help?"), or do not know exactly
   what they are looking for ("Has anyone seen a problem like this
   before?")  To support browsing and casual queries, &qmtrack; will
   provide a "drill-down" model as well in the web interface, in which
   query results may subsequently be narrowed down with additional
   query restrictions.</para>

  </section>

  <section>
   <title>Notification</title>

   <para>A third significant feature of &qmtrack; is its use of <link
   linkend="def-trigger">triggers</link> to support customized event
   handling.  Triggers are operations that are invoked on certain
   kinds of events.  Trigger parameters can be configured, and new
   triggers created, during &qmtrack;'s installation, or after it is
   in place.</para>

   <para>When &qmtrack; is about to access, create, or modify an item,
   it first calls any triggers that have been registered for that
   operation on that class.  Any trigger may abort the operation if it
   is invalid or unauthorized.</para>

   <para>If none of the triggers raises an exception, &qmtrack;
   completes the operation. After it's done, it then calls additional
   triggers that have been registered for the operation.  Together,
   these triggers allow sites to log extra information about issue
   modification for auditing purposes, implement site-specific
   security or authorization policies, interact with legacy issue
   databases or reporting frameworks, and other important side
   effects.</para>

  </section>

 </section>

</chapter>

<!--
  Local Variables:
  indent-tabs-mode: nil
  sgml-indent-step: 1 
  sgml-always-quote-attributes: t
  sgml-general-insert-case: lower
  sgml-minimize-attributes: nil
  sgml-parent-document: ("qmtrack.xml" "book" "chapter")
  End:
-->
