<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

  File:   core.xml
  Author: Mark Mitchell, Greg Wilson, Alex Samuel
  Date:   2000-11-01

  Contents:
    Core QMTest implementation.

  Copyright (C) 2000 CodeSourcery LLC.  This material may
  be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions set forth in
  the Software Carpentry Open Publication License, which is available at:

    http://www.software-carpentry.com/openpub-license.html

-->
<chapter><title>&QMTest; Core Implementation</title>
  
 <para>This chapter describes the Python implementation of the core
 QMTest components.  For some components, many implementations are
 envisioned; the requirements for these implementations are
 given.</para>
  
 <section><title>Test representation</title>
   
  <section><title>Test class implementations</title>

   <para>Each QMTest test class is implemented as a Python class.
   Though QMTest does not recognize any notion of test class
   inheritance, this may be produced in effect via Python class
   inheritance.</para>

   <para>A test class should have the following members:
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>An initialization method (<function>__init__</function>),
      that is used to instantiate test instances.  Test instances are
      Python instances of the Python class corresponding to the test
      class.  The parameters of the <function>__init__</function>
      method are the test class parameters.  All parameters must be
      named; positional parameters are not allowed.  A final
      <token>**</token> parameter is allowed.</para>

      <para>If a new test class is created via inheritance from a
      previous test class, the derived <function>__init__</function>
      is expected to invoke the base class
      <function>__init__</function>, passing unused parameters.</para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>An <function>is_valid</function> method.  This method
      takes a <classname>Configuration</classname> object and returns
      as boolean whether the particular test instance is appropriate
      to run on that configuration.</para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>A <function>run</function> method.  The
      <function>run</function> method is passed the same configuration
      that was previously validated by the same test instance's
      <function>is_valid</function> method.
      <!-- FIXME: What are the parameters to the run method? -->
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </para>

   <para>After this point, we will use the term test to refer to the
   corresponding Python class sometimes, when there is no
   ambiguity.</para>

   <para>Instantiating a test instance requires locating and
   instantiating test class.  This is done via these two methods:
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>The test class is located in the Python execution
      environment in the usual way, using the
      <envar>PYTHONPATH</envar> mechanism.</para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>If the class has not been found, the test is asked to
      locate the test class.  The test database is provided with the
      name of the test class and also with the test identifier being
      instantiated.  (This allows the test database to handle relative
      paths in its conceptual tree, between the test id and the test
      class.)</para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>

  </section>

  <section><title>Test records</title>

   <para>Test records are represented by instances of the class
   <classname>QMTest.TestRecord</classname>.  This class has the
   following members:</para>

   <para><programlisting>
<![CDATA[
class TestRecord:
   """The canonical representation of a test."""

   def GetId(self):
       """Return the test id of this test."""

   def GetClassName(self):
       """Return the name of the test class of which this is an
       instance."""

   def GetArguments(self):
       """Returns the arguments to the test class.  Arguments are
       presented as a mapping from text argument names to argument
       values.  Argument values are text Python expressions."""

   def GetCategories(self):
       """Return a sequence of names of categories to which this test
       belongs."""

   def GetPrerequisites(self):
       """Return a sequence of pairs representing prerequisite tests
       for this test.  The first element of the pair is the test id
       of the prerequisite test.  The second element is the outcome
       that that test must produce for the prerequisite to be
       considered met.  If the second element is None, any outcome is
       considered sufficient."""

   def GetPreactions(self):
       """Return a sequence of action ids of actions that must be run
       and produce a successful outcome before this test is run."""

   def GetPostactions(self):
       """Return a sequence of action ids of actions that must be run
       after this test is run."""

   def GetDesignTimeArguments(self):
       """Fix me."""
]]>
   </programlisting></para>
   
   <para>Note that test record objects are not polymorphic, regardless
   of the test class of the test.</para>

   <para>Test records are the representation of tests that are stored
   in and returned by test databases.  Most test database
   implementations will externalize test records to a persistent
   store.  The preferred text-based format for doing this is
   XML.</para>

   <para>An XML DTD for storing tests can be quite simple.  Arguments
   are stored as CDATA, and are evaluated as Python expressions or
   treated as text literals.  Below is the canonical DTD for storing
   test records.
    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT test
    ( class, 
      ( argument | category | prerequisite | preaction | postaction )* 
    )
>

<!ELEMENT class (#PCDATA)>

<!ELEMENT argument (#PCDATA)>
<!ATTLIST argument
    name CDATA #REQUIRED
    type ( expression | text ) #IMPLIED
>

<!ELEMENT category (#PCDATA)>

<!ELEMENT prerequisite (#PCDATA)>

<!ELEMENT preaction (#PCDATA)>

<!ELEMENT postaction (#PCDATA)>
]]>
    </programlisting>
   </para>


   <!-- The following is ugly since we want to put a literal 
        <![CDATA[ ... ]]> marked section inside the marked section of 
        this document.  -->
   <para>For example, a test record might be stored like this:
    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<QMTest.test>
 <class>compile_link_run</class>
 <argument name="input" type="text">
<![CDATA[
int main ()
{
  volatile int x = 2;
  return x - 2;
}]]>
]]&gt;<![CDATA[
 </argument>
 <argument name="flags">'-O%d -fpic' % get_optimization_level ()</argument>
 <category>C</category>
 <category>back end</category>
 <category>PIC</category>
 <category>optimization</category>
 <prerequisite>torture.link.test123</prerequisite>
</QMTest.test>
]]>
   </programlisting></para>

  </section>

  <section><title>Test instances</title>

   <para>A <firstterm>test instance</firstterm> is an instance of a
   test classes.  For a test to be run, a test instance must be
   created.  To do this, the test class is first obtained from the
   test class name stored in the test record.  The test arguments are
   extracted from the test record and evaluated in the test-time
   execution context.  The results are passed to the initialization
   function of the test class to create the instance.  To run the
   test, the instance's run method is invoked.</para>
   
  </section>

 </section>

 <section>
  <title>The test system</title>

  <section><title>Action implementation</title>

   <para>
   <!-- FIXME: Same as test implementation, except we do somethign
   different with the outcomes, right?  Or is there a different set
   of outcomes for actions? -->
   </para>

  </section>

  <section><title>Test result implementation</title>

   <para></para>

  </section>

 </section>

</chapter>

<!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: sgml
  indent-tabs-mode: nil
  sgml-indent-step: 1 
  sgml-always-quote-attributes: t
  sgml-general-insert-case: lower
  sgml-minimize-attributes: nil
  sgml-parent-document: ("QMTest.xml" "book" "chapter")
  End:
-->
