<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Doc style="sapcat" abbrevs="sapcat_abbrevs">

   <title>Proposal for SapCat: Site and Platform Customization
   Administration Tool</title>

<h1>Proposal for SapCat: Site and Platform Customization Administration Tool</h1>
<address>
	<a href="http://www.rpi.edu/~toddr/">R. Lindsay Todd, Ph.D.</a><br/>
	P.O.&nbsp;Box&nbsp;75<br/>
	Sand&nbsp;Lake, NY 12153-0075<br/>
	<a href="mailto:l.todd@acm.org">l.todd@acm.org</a>
</address>

<abstract>
<p>
    We present the {:sapcat:} system, a tool to help make software
    portable.  Programmers can parameterize their source code with
    macros or symbols that indicate the results of feature probes.
    {:sapcat:} will automatically scan the source code for occurrences
    of these symbols, perform operating system probes, and adapt files
    to make sure the correct values for these symbols are used.  In
    some cases, {:sapcat:} can even generate <q>bootstrap scripts</q>
    that will perform these probes and substitutions, even on systems
    without {:sapcat:} or {:python:}.
</p>
<p>
    {:sapcat:} relies on a <q>package description database</q>, a
    collection of files created by the package developer.  This
    database indicates dependencies between objects and their
    immediate sources, optional features of the package, and
    information regarding how to contact the maintainer.  From the
    dependency information, {:sapcat:} is able to both determine
    source files to be scanned and interact with the build system.
</p>
<p>
    While easy for programmers, we take care not neglect the final end
    users, those who will be using {:sapcat:} to tailor their
    software.  We provide <q>casual installers</q> with an
    installation wizard, and a command line interface for
    <q>professional systems administrators</q> who need to script
    their operations.  We even consider <q>systems integrators</q> who
    wish to create binary distributions of packages.
</p>
</abstract>

<contents/>

<include file="sapcat_intro.xml" target="sub"/>
<include file="sapcat_req.xml" target="sub"/>
<include file="sapcat_over.xml" target="sub"/>
<include file="sapcat_design.xml" target="sub"/>
<include file="sapcat_devplan.xml" target="sub"/>
<include file="sapcat_summary.xml" target="sub"/>
<include file="sapcat_app_ideas.xml" target="sub"/>
<include file="sapcat_app_decisions.xml" target="sub"/>

<footnotes/>


<hr/>
<address><a href="mailto:l.todd@acm.org">R. Lindsay Todd</a></address>
<!-- Created: Thu Jun  8 15:40:08 EDT 2000 -->
<!-- hhmts start -->
Last modified: Fri Jun 30, 2000
<!-- hhmts end -->
<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- mode: xml -->
<!-- End: -->
</Doc>
