<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>

<Doc style="sapcat" abbrevs="sapcat_abbrevs">
<title>SapCat: Summary and Acknowledgements</title>
<h1>SapCat: Summary and Acknowledgements</h1>

<contents/>

<subdoc name="sub">

<h2 key="scSummary">Summary and Acknowledgements</h2>
<p>
    We have presented a proposal and design for a software tailoring
    tool called {:sapcat:}.  This tool helps programmers write
    portable code, by providing feature tests and macros they may use
    in their programs, scanning their programs to determine which
    features need be tested, assisting in writing portable build
    scripts, and creating {:srcdists:}.  {:sapcat:} helps busy system
    administrators by providing the mechanism needed to tailor and
    build packages requiring a great control, without needing constant
    interactions.  It helps system administrators unfamiliar with a
    package to determine what features need customizization, thus
    assisting them in making intelligent choices.  It helps systems
    integrators create {:bindists:}.  Finally, our design of an
    installation wizard should make it installing Open Source software
    nearly as simple, and far more flexible, than it currently is to
    install binary packages on {:windows:} or {:linux:}.
</p>
<p>
    On a personal note, we have found the Software Carpentry
    competition extremely stimulating and rewarding.  We hope to see
    more further competitions of this sort, and look forward to seeing
    the fruit of this first round.
</p>
<p>
    I would also like to thank my colleagues at {:RPI:} with whom I
    have had many enjoyable discussions about software customization
    issues, particularly Mike Douglas, Garance Drosehn, Alan Powell,
    and Mike Sofka.  I also want to thank my manager, Gary Schwartz,
    for allowing me to take <q>vacation</q> time during a particularly
    busy time, and my family, who have graciously allowed me many
    hours to hide in the <q>abyss</q> to work on this proposal.
</p>


</subdoc>
<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- mode: xml -->
<!-- End: -->
</Doc>
