<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

  File:   concepts.xml
  Author: Stefan Seefeld
  Date:   2006-05-01

  Contents:
    Introduction to QMTest.

  Copyright (C) 2006 CodeSourcery Inc.

-->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "qmtest.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="concepts">
  <title><application>QMTest</application> Concepts</title>

  <para>This section presents the concepts that underlie
  <application>QMTest</application>'s design. By understanding these concepts,
  you will be able to better understand how <application>QMTest</application>
  works. In addition, you will find it easier to extend
  <application>QMTest</application> to new application domains.</para>

  <para>The central principle underlying the design of QMTest is that
  the problem of testing can be divided into a domain-dependent problem
  and a domain-independent problem.  The domain-dependent problem is
  deciding what to test and how to test it.  For example, should a
  database be tested by performing unit tests on the C code that makes
  up the database, or by performing integration tests using SQL queries?
  How should the output of a query asking for a set of records be
  compared to expected output?  Does the order in which records are
  presented matter?  These are questions that only someone who
  understands the application domain can answer.</para>

  <para>The domain-independent part of the problem is managing the
  creation of tests, executing the tests, and displaying the results for
  users.  For example, how does a user create a new test?  How are tests
  stored?  Should failing tests be reported to the user, even if the
  failure was expected?  These questions are independent of the
  application domain; they are just as relevant for compiler tests as
  they are for database tests.</para>

  <para>QMTest is intended to solve the domain-independent part of the
  problem and to offer a convenient, powerful, and flexible interface
  for solving the domain-dependent problem.  QMTest is both a complete
  application, in that it can be used <quote>out of the box</quote> to
  handle many testing domains, and infrastructure, in that it can be
  extended to handle other domains.</para>

  <para>Throughout this chapter we will use the <application>qmtest</application>
    application with a variety of parameters and options. For a full description
    of the <application>qmtest</application> please refer to the
    <link linkend="app-command-line">command-line reference</link>.</para>

  <para>The following commands create a simple <link linkend="concepts-test-database">test database</link>
  in the current working directory. This test database will be used throughout the
  following sections of this tutorial.</para>

  <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>mkdir tdb</userinput>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>cd tdb</userinput>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest create-tdb</userinput>
  </screen>

  <section id="concepts-tests">
    <title>Tests</title>

    <para>A <firstterm>test</firstterm> checks for the correct behavior of the
    target application. What constitutes correct behavior will vary depending
    on the application domain. For example, correct behavior for a database
    might mean that it is able to retrieve records correctly while correct
    behavior for a compiler might mean that it generates correct object code
    from input source code.</para>

    <para>Every test has a name that uniquely identifies the test, within a
    given <link linkend="concepts-test-database">test database</link>. Test
    names must be composed entirely of lowercase letters, numbers, the
    <quote>_</quote> character, and the <quote>.</quote> character. You can
    think of test names like file names. The <quote>.</quote> character takes
    the place of <quote>/</quote>; it allows you to place a test in a
    particular <firstterm>directory</firstterm>. For example, the test name
    <filename>a.b.c</filename> names a test named <filename>c</filename> in
    the directory <filename>a.b</filename>. The directory
    <filename>a.b</filename> is a subdirectory of the directory
    <filename>a</filename>.</para>

    <para>Every test is an instance of some test class. The test class
    dictates how the test is run, what constitutes success, and what
    constitutes failure. For example, the
    <classname>command.ExecTest</classname> class that comes with
    <application>QMTest</application> executes the target application and
    looks at its output. The test passes if the actual output exactly matches
    the expected output.</para>

    <para>The arguments to the test parameterize the test; they are what make
    two instances of the same test class different from each other. For
    example, the arguments to <classname>command.ExecTest</classname> indicate
    which application to run, what command-line arguments to provide, and what
    output is expected.</para>

    <para>The <classname>python.ExecTest</classname> class is similar to 
    <classname>command.ExecTest</classname>, but, instead of executing a 
    command using the system shell, it evaluates an expression in the Python 
    programming language.  The test passes if (and only if) the expression is true.
    In Python, the expressions <code>True</code> and <code>False</code> are 
    literals.</para>

    <para>The following creates two trivial tests, <varname>python_pass</varname> 
    and <varname>python_fail</varname>:</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest create --id=python_pass -a expression='True' test python.ExecTest
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest create --id=python_fail -a expression='False' test python.ExecTest
    </screen>

    <para>The first test will always pass while the second will always fail.</para>

    <para>The <command>qmtest ls</command> command will show the content of the 
    test database:</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest ls
python_fail
python_pass
    </screen>
    <para>Similar to the Unix <command>ls</command> command, the <option>-l</option> option
      can be used to provide a detailed listing, with kind ("test", "resource", or "suite"),
      extension class, and id:</para>
    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest ls -l
test python.ExecTest python_fail
test python.ExecTest python_pass
    </screen>

    <section id="sec-running-tests">
      <title>Running Tests</title>

      <para>To run one or more tests, use the
      <command><command>qmtest</command> run</command> command:</para>
      <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest run</userinput>
      </screen>
      <para>Each invocation of the <command><command>qmtest</command> run</command>
      command is a single test run, and produces a single set of test results
      and statistics. Specify as arguments the names of tests and test suites
      to run. Even if you specify a test more than once, either directly or by
      incorporation in a test suite, <application>QMTest</application> runs it
      only once.</para>

      <para>If you wish to run all tests in the test database, use the
      implicit test suite <literal>.</literal> (a single period; see <xref
      linkend="concepts-implicit-test-suites" />), or omit all IDs from the
      command line.</para>

      <para><application>QMTest</application> can run tests in multiple
      concurrent threads of execution or on multiple remote hosts. See the
      documentation for the <link
      linkend="sec-testcmd-run"><command>run</command> command</link> for
      details.</para>

      <para>How the output of the <command><command>qmtest</command> run</command>
      command should be interpreted will be discussed in <xref linkend="concepts-test-results"/>.</para>
    </section><!-- Running tests -->

    <section id="concepts-tests-prereqs">
      <title>Prerequisite Tests</title>

      <para>QMTest can avoid running one test (a "dependent test") when some
      other test (a "prerequisite test") has a particular outcome.</para>

      <para>Suppose that you have a test database with a very simple test that
      can be run very quickly, and a very complex test that takes hours to
      run. You know that if the simple test fails, then there is no chance
      that the complex test will pass. In that case, you could make the simple
      test a prerequisite of the complex test. Then, when you run both tests,
      QMTest will run the simple test first. If it fails, the complex test
      will not be run at all.</para>

      <para>Alternatively, suppose that you have a very comprehensive test
      that tests ten features of your software. You also have ten separate
      tests, one for each feature. The comprehensive test can be run in one
      minute; runnning the separate tests takes two minutes each. So, you want
      to run the comprehensive test first; if it passes, there is no need to
      run the individual tests. However, if the comprehensive test fails, you
      may want to run the single tests to isolate the problem. In this case,
      each of the simple tests would have the comprehensive test as a
      prerequisite, indicating that the simple test should be run only if the
      comprehensive test fails.</para>

      <para>If you explicitly run just the dependent test, QMTest will not run
      the prerequisite test automatically. In other words, prerequisites are
      an optimization; when running both the prerequisite and the dependent
      test, QMTest will run them in the order you've implied, and can omit the
      dependent test if it is not useful. But, QMTest will not automatically
      force you to run the prerequisite tests when you only want to run the
      dependent test.</para>

      <para>Because prerequisite tests are not run unless you ask for them,
      the dependent test should not depend in any way on the prerequisite
      test. Otherwise, users will see different test outcomes when they run
      the dependent test by itself. In other words, each test should stand
      alone; the order in which tests are run should not affect their
      outcomes.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sec-ordering-and-dependencies">
      <title>Ordering and Dependencies</title>

      <para>Given one or more input test names and test suite names,
      <application>QMTest</application> employs the following procedure to
      determine which tests and resources to run and the order in which they
      are run.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><application>QMTest</application> resolves test names and
          test suite names. Test suites are expanded into the tests they
          contain. Since test suites may contain other test suites, this
          process is repeated until all test suites have been expanded. The
          result is a set of tests that are to be run.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><application>QMTest</application> computes a schedule for
          running the tests to be run such that a test's prerequisites are
          run before the test itself is run. Prerequisites not included in
          the test run are ignored. Outside of this condition, the order in
          which tests are run is undefined.</para>

          <para>If <application>QMTest</application> is invoked to run tests
          in parallel or distributed across several <link
          linkend="def-target">targets</link>, the tests are distributed
          among them as well. <application>QMTest</application> does not
          guarantee that a test's prerequisites are run on the same target,
          though. On each target, tests are assigned to the next available
          concurrent process or thread.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><application>QMTest</application> determines the required
          resources for the tests to be run. If several tests require the
          same resource, <application>QMTest</application> attempts to run
          all of the tests on the same target. In this case, the resource is
          set up and cleaned up only once. In some cases,
          <application>QMTest</application> may schedule the tests on
          multiple targets; in that case, the resource is set up and cleaned
          up once on each target.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>In the following cases, a test or resource will not be executed,
      even though it is included in the set of tests enumerated
      above:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A test specifies for each of its prerequisite tests an
          expected outcome. If the prerequisite is included in the test run
          and the actual outcome of the prerequisite test is different from
          the expected outcome, the test is not run. Instead, it is given an
          <symbol>UNTESTED</symbol> outcome.</para>

          <para>If a test's prerequisite is not included in the test run,
          that prerequisite is ignored.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If a setup function for one of the resources required by a
          test fails, the test is given an <symbol>UNTESTED</symbol>
          outcome.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The cleanup function of a resource is run after the last
          test that requires that resource, whether or not that test was
          run. The cleanup function is run even if the setup function
          failed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section><!-- Ordering and Dependencies -->
  </section><!-- concepts-tests -->

  <section id="concepts-test-results">
    <title>Test Results</title>

    <para>A <firstterm id="def-result">result</firstterm> is an <firstterm
    id="def-outcome">outcome</firstterm> together with some
    <firstterm>annotations</firstterm>. The outcome indicates whether the test
    passed or failed. The annotations give additional information about the
    result, such as the manner in which the test failed, the output the test
    produced, or the amount of time it took to run the test.</para>

    <section id="concepts-outcomes">
      <title>Outcomes</title>

      <para>The outcome of a test indicates whether it passed or failed, or
      whether some exceptional event occurred. There are four test outcomes:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><symbol>PASS</symbol>: The test succeeded.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><symbol>FAIL</symbol>: The test failed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><symbol>ERROR</symbol>: A problem occurred in the test
          execution environment, rather than in the tested system. For
          example, this outcome is used when the test class attempted to run
          an executable in order to test it, but could not because the
          system call to create a new process failed.</para>

          <para>This outcome may also indicate a defect in
          <application>QMTest</application> or in the test class.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><symbol>UNTESTED</symbol>: <application>QMTest</application>
          did not attempt to execute the test. For example, this outcome is
          used when <application>QMTest</application> determines that a
          prerequisite test failed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Thus, running <application>QMTest</application> with the two
      previously defined tests will result in the following output:</para>
      <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest run</userinput>
...
--- TEST RESULTS -------------------------------------------------------------

  python_fail                                   : FAIL
    Expression evaluates to false.

  python_pass                                   : PASS

...
--- STATISTICS ---------------------------------------------------------------

       2        tests total
       1 ( 50%) tests FAIL
       1 ( 50%) tests PASS
      </screen>
      <para> In addition, the results are stored in a results file 
        (<filename>results.qmr</filename> by default).</para>
    </section><!-- concepts-outcomes -->

    <section id="concepts-annotations">
      <title>Annotations</title>

      <para>An annotation is a key/value pair. Both the keys and values are
      strings. The value is HTML. When a test (or resource) runs it may add
      annotations to the result. These annotations are displayed by
      <application>QMTest</application> and preserved in the results file. If
      you write your own test class, you can use annotations to store
      information that will make your test class more informative.</para>
    </section><!-- concepts-annotations -->

    <section id="concepts-expectations">
      <title>Expectations</title>

      <para>The easiest way to create expectations is to tell
      <application>QMTest</application> that you expect future results to be
      the same as the results you just obtained. Thus, <application>QMTest</application>
      accepts result files obtained from prior test runs as expectations.</para>

      <para>Thus, rerunning <application>QMTest</application>, but using
      <filename>results.qmr</filename> as expectations, the test results are 
      displayed differently:</para>

      <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest run -O results.qmr</userinput>
...
--- TEST RESULTS -------------------------------------------------------------

  python_fail                                   : XFAIL
    Expression evaluates to false.

  python_pass                                   : PASS

...
--- TESTS WITH UNEXPECTED OUTCOMES -------------------------------------------

  None.


--- STATISTICS ---------------------------------------------------------------

       2 (100%) tests as expected

    </screen>
    </section><!-- concepts-expectations -->
  </section><!-- concepts-test-results -->

  <section id="concepts-test-suite">
    <title>Test Suites</title>

    <para>A <firstterm>test suite</firstterm> is a collection of tests.
    <application>QMTest</application> can run an entire test suite at once, so
    by grouping tests together in a test suite, you make it easier to run a
    number of tests at once. A single test can be a member of more than one
    test suite. A test suite can contain other test suites; the total set of
    tests in a test suite includes both those tests included directly and
    those tests included as part of another test suite. Every test suite has a
    name, following the same conventions given above for tests.</para>

    <para>One use of test suites is to provide groups of tests that are run in
    different situations. For example, the <literal>nightly</literal> test
    suite might consist of those tests that should be run automatically every
    night, while the <literal>checkin</literal> test suite might consist of
    those tests that have to pass before any changes are made to the target
    application.</para>

    <section id="concepts-implicit-test-suites">
      <title>Implicit Test Suites</title>

      <para><xref linkend="concepts-tests" /> explains how you may arrange
      tests in a tree hierarchy, using a period
      (<quote><literal>.</literal></quote>) as the path separator in test
      names. <application>QMTest</application> defines an <firstterm>implicit
      test suite</firstterm> for each directory. The name of these implicit
      test suites is the same as the name of the directory. The implicit test
      suite corresponding to a directory contains all tests in that directory
      or its subdirectories.</para>
  
      <para>Let us create some more tests, but this time within their respective
        subdirectories:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest create --id=dir1.one -a expression='True' test python.ExecTest
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest create --id=dir1.two -a expression='False' test python.ExecTest
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest create --id=dir2.one -a expression='True' test python.ExecTest
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest create --id=dir2.dir3.one -a expression='False' test python.ExecTest
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest create --id=dir2.dir3.two -a expression='False' test python.ExecTest
      </screen>

      <para>This will create five new tests, together with three directories:</para>
      <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest ls -lR
directory                 dir1
test      python.ExecTest dir1.one
test      python.ExecTest dir1.two
directory                 dir2
directory                 dir2.dir3
test      python.ExecTest dir2.dir3.one
test      python.ExecTest dir2.dir3.two
test      python.ExecTest dir2.one
      </screen>      
 
      <para>These directories are implicit suites, i.e. it is possible to only address
        tests within them:</para>
      <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest ls -lR dir2
directory                 dir2
directory                 dir2.dir3
test      python.ExecTest dir2.dir3.one
test      python.ExecTest dir2.dir3.two
test      python.ExecTest dir2.one
      </screen>      

      <para>The suite named "<filename>.</filename>" (a single period) is the
      implicit test suite corresponding to the root directory in the test
      database. This suite therefore contains all tests in the database. For
      example, the command <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest run .</userinput>
    </screen> is equivalent to: <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest run</userinput>
    </screen> Both commands run all tests in the database.</para>
    </section>

    <!-- concepts-implicit-test-suites -->
    <section id="concepts-explicit-test-suites">
      <title>Explicit Test Suites</title>
  
      <para>Explicit test suites are a means to refer to a set of tests for the purpose of executing them
        together, no matter how they are organized in the test database. For example, you may want to
        run a subset of all tests nightly. To do this, you create a suite, listing all tests (as well as
        contained suites) explicitely:</para>

      <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest create --id=nightly suite explicit_suite.ExplicitSuite(test_ids="['dir1.one', 'dir2.one']",
                                                                suite_ids="['dir2.dir3']")
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest ls -l
directory                              dir1
directory                              dir2
suite     explicit_suite.ExplicitSuite nightly
<prompt>&gt; </prompt>qmtest ls -l nightly
test      python.ExecTest dir1.one
directory                 dir2.dir3
test      python.ExecTest dir2.one
      </screen>

    </section><!-- concepts-explicit-test-suites -->
  </section>


  <!-- concepts-test-suite -->

  <section id="concepts-test-database">
    <title>Test Database</title>

    <para>A <firstterm id="def-test-database">test database</firstterm> stores
    tests, test suites, and other entities. When you ask
    <application>QMTest</application> for a particular test by name, it
    queries the test database to obtain the test itself.
    <application>QMTest</application> stores a test database in a single
    directory, which may include many files and subdirectories.</para>

    <para>In general, <application>QMTest</application> can only use one test
    database at a time. However, it is possible to create a test database
    which contains other test databases. This mechanism allows you to store
    the tests associated with different parts of a large application in
    different test databases, and still combine them into a single large test
    database when required.</para>

    <para>A single test database can store many different kinds of tests. By
    default, <application>QMTest</application> stores tests, test suites, and
    all other entities in the test database using subdirectories containing XML
    files. Generally, there should be no need to examine or modify these files
    directly. However, the use of an XML format makes it easy for you to
    automatically generate tests from another program, if required.</para>
  </section><!-- concepts-test-database -->

  <section id="concepts-context">
    <title>Context</title>

    <para>When you create a test, you choose arguments for the test. The test
    class uses this information to run the test. However, the test class may
    sometimes need information that is not available when the test is created.
    For example, if you are writing compiler tests to verify conformance with
    the C programming language specification, you do not know the location of
    the C compiler itself. The C compiler may be installed in different
    locations on different machines.</para>

    <para>A <firstterm id="def-context">context</firstterm> gives users a way
    of conveying this kind of information to tests. The context is a set of
    key/value pairs. The keys are always strings. The values of all context
    properties provided by the user are strings. In general, all tests in a
    given use of <application>QMTest</application> will have the same context.
    However, when a resource is set up, it may place additional information in
    the context of those tests that depend upon it. The values inserted by the
    resource may have any type, so long as they can be "pickled" by
    Python.</para>

    <para>All context properties whose names begin with
    "<literal>qmtest.</literal>" are reserved for use by
    <application>QMTest</application>. The values inserted by
    <application>QMTest</application> may have any type. Test and resource
    classes should not depend on the presence or absence of these
    properites.</para>

    <para>To understand how a context is used during the execution of a test let us
      start by creating a somewhat less trivial test:</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest create --id compile test 
    compilation_test.CompilationTest(executable="compile", source_files="['/path/to/compile.cc']")"</userinput>
    </screen>

    <para>When run, this test will compile <filename>/path/to/compile.cc</filename> and run 
      the resulting executable. The test passes if compilation succeeds, and the program
      exit status indicates success.</para>

    <para>The <classname>compilation_test.CompilationTest</classname> test class requires that the
    compiler be available in the context with the key <varname>CompilationTest.compiler_path</varname>.
    You can provide a context variable to QMTest either through a context file or on the
    command-line using the -c option. For example:</para>
    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest run -c CompilationTest.compiler_path=g++ compile</userinput>
    </screen>
    <para>will run the test using the <command>g++</command> compiler, while:</para>
    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest run -c CompilationTest.compiler_path=/bin/CC compile</userinput>
    </screen>
    <para>will run the test with the <command>/bin/CC</command> compiler.</para>
  </section> <!-- concepts-context -->

  <section id="concepts-resources">
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>Some tests take a lot of work to set up. For example, a database
    test that checks the result of SQL queries may require that the database
    first be populated with a substantial number of records. If there are many
    tests that all use the same set of records, it would be wasteful to set up
    the database for each test. It would be more efficient to set up the
    database once, run all of the tests, and then remove the databases upon
    completion.</para>

    <para>You can use a <firstterm>resource</firstterm> to gain this
    efficiency. If a test depends on a resource,
    <application>QMTest</application> will ensure that the resource is
    available before the test runs. Once all tests that depend on the resource
    have been run <application>QMTest</application> will destroy the
    resource.</para>

    <para>Just as every test is an instance of a <firstterm>test
    class</firstterm>, every resource is an instance of a <firstterm>resource
    class</firstterm>. The resource class explains how to set up the resource
    and how to clean up when it is no longer needed. The arguments to the
    resource class are what make two instances of the same resource class
    different from each other. For example, in the case of a resource that
    sets up a database, the records to place in the database might be given as
    arguments. Every resource has a name, using the same format that is used
    for tests.</para>

    <para>Under some circumstances (such as running tests on multiple 
    <link linkend="concepts-targets">targets</link> at once),
    <application>QMTest</application> may create more than one
    instance of the same resource. Therefore, you should never depend on there
    being only one instance of a resource. In addition, if you have asked
    <application>QMTest</application> to run tests concurrently, two tests may
    access the same resource at the same time. You can, however, be assured
    that there will be only one instance of a particular resource on a
    particular target at any one time.</para>

    <para>Tests have limited access to the resources on which they depend. A
    resource may place additional information into the context (<xref
    linkend="concepts-context" />) that is visible to the test. However, the
    actual resource object itself is not available to tests. (The reason for
    this limitiation is that for a target consisting of multiple processes,
    the resource object may not be located in the same process as the test that
    depends upon it.)</para>

    <para>Setting up or cleaning up a resource produces a result, just like
    those produced for tests. <application>QMTest</application> will display
    these results in its summary output and record them in the results
    file.</para>

    <para>Building on the previous example of a CompilationTest, let us
      consider a situation where some test application should be run multiple
      times with different arguments. The test application, however, needs to
      be compiled first. In order to avoid recompiling the application for each
      test, you can create a resource that compiles the application once.  Then,
      tests that depend on this resource can assume that the application has 
      already been built.  The following commands:</para>
    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest create --id applet resource
    compilation_test.CompiledResource(executable="applet", source_files="['/path/to/applet.cc']")</userinput>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest create --id run_applet_0 test
    compilation_test.ExecutableTest(args="['0']", resources="['applet']")</userinput>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest create --id run_applet_1 test
    compilation_test.ExecutableTest(args="['1']", resources="['applet']")</userinput>
    </screen>
    <para>create a resource (named "applet") for the application and two tests
    ("run_applet_0" and "run_applet_1"), both of which make use of
    "applet", but which pass it different command-line options.</para>
    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest run -c CompilationTest.compiler_path=g++ run_applet_0 run_applet_1</userinput>
--- TEST RESULTS -------------------------------------------------------------

  Setup applet                                  : PASS

  run_applet_0                                  : PASS

  run_applet_1                                  : PASS

  Cleanup applet                                : PASS
    </screen>
  </section> <!-- concepts-resources -->

  <section id="concepts-targets">
    <title>Targets</title>

    <para>A <firstterm id="def-target">target</firstterm> is
    <application>QMTest</application>'s abstraction of a machine. By using
    multiple targets, you can run your tests on multiple machines at once. If
    you have many tests, and many machines, you can greatly reduce the amount
    of time it takes to run all of your tests by distributing the tests across
    multiple targets.</para>

    <para>By default, <application>QMTest</application> uses only one target:
    the machine on which you are running <application>QMTest</application>.
    You may specify other targets by creating a target file, which lists the
    available targets and their attributes, and specifying the target file
    when you invoke <command>qmtest</command>.</para>

    <para>Each target is a member of a single <firstterm
    id="def-target-group">target group</firstterm>. All targets in the same
    target group are considered equivalent. A target group is specified by a
    string. If you are testing software on multiple platforms at once, the
    target group might correspond to machines running the same operating
    system. For example, all Intel 80386 compatible machines running GNU/Linux
    might be in the <quote><literal>i386-pc-linux-gnu</literal></quote> target
    group.</para>

    <para><application>QMTest</application> by default executes all tests
    using a 'serial target', i.e. one after another. This behavior can be
    changed by specifying a different concurrency strategy, such as one that
    uses multiple threads, multiple processes, or even multiple physical
    machines.</para>

    <screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><userinput>qmtest create-target -a name=local -a group=local -a threads=2 a thread_target.ThreadTarget</userinput>
   </screen>

    <para>This creates a 'thread target' where two threads are used to run
    the tests in parallel.</para>
  </section> <!-- concepts-targets -->

  <section id="concepts-hosts">
    <title>Hosts</title>
    <para>Sometime it is necessary to execute a test application on a different machine 
    than the one running the <application>qmtest</application> application itself. For
    example, if the test involves executing an application previously cross-compiled,
    the binary needs to be uploaded to an appropriate host and run there.</para>
    <para><application>QMTest</application> provides a <firstterm id="def-host">host</firstterm>
    abstraction for this purpose. To use this mechanism, test classes need to provide explicit support for it.
    A number of built-in test classes support cross-testing.</para>
    <para>To run the <varname>compile</varname> test on a remote target
    machine, specify a <varname>CompilationTest.target</varname> variable in
    the context file to contain a host descriptor:</para>

    <programlisting>
CompilationTest.compiler=/path/to/cross_compiler
CompilationTest.target=ssh_host.SSHHost(host_name="192.168.0.100")
   </programlisting>
   <para>This will run the compiled executable on the machine with the IP address
     <code>192.168.0.100</code>, using ssh for communication.</para>
  </section> <!-- concepts-hosts -->
</chapter>
