<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

  File:   requirements.xml
  Author: R. Lindsay Todd
  Date:   2000-11-11

  Contents:
    Requirements for the qmconfig design documents.

  Copyright (C) 2000 CodeSourcery LLC.  This material may
  be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions set forth in
  the Software Carpentry Open Publication License, which is available at:

    http://www.software-carpentry.com/openpub-license.html

-->
<chapter id="chap-requirements">
 <title>Requirements</title>

 <para>In this chapter, we present the requirements we have identified
 for &qmconfig;.</para>

 <section id="sec-requirements-terminology">
  <title>Terminology</title>

  <para>The process of preparing software to run on a particular
  platform has been variously called configuring, tailoring, or
  customizing.  Wordsmiths may debate how to best use these terms.
  Our preference (after studying dictionary definitions) is to call
  this process of specifying site conventions, specifying local
  preferences for options, and adapting to the platform, <firstterm
  id="D-tailoring">tailoring</firstterm> or
  <firstterm>customization</firstterm>.<footnote><para>We recognize
  that <quote>configuration</quote> would be a fine term for this
  process.  But our choice of terminology now will affect our natural
  choices of file names, etc. later.  We thought it desirable to
  ultimately use different names than &Qautoconf; and &Qmetaconfig;
  had used.  It also leads to a nice noun, <quote>tailor</quote>, to
  refer to a person who is is tailoring the
  software.</para></footnote> We will call the process of setting up
  site-wide files, e.g., the <filename>sendmail.cf</filename> file
  needed by &QFsendmail;, <firstterm
  id="D-configure">configuration</firstterm>.  Finally, we will call
  the process of setting a user's personal preferences, <firstterm
  id="D-personalize">personalizing</firstterm>.</para>

  <para>We call a deliverable unit of software source code a
  <firstterm id="D-kit">source kit</firstterm> (or frequently, just a
  <firstterm>kit</firstterm>).  A kit is generally distributed in some
  bundled manner, such as in a &QFzip;, &QFrpm;, or compressed &QFtar;
  archive.  Such a bundled kits is called a <firstterm
  id="D-srcdist">source distribution</firstterm>.  A source
  distribution can be unpacked into a kit, which in turn can be
  tailored, compiled, and installed on a platform.  Alternatively, the
  installation step can be omitted, and the files that would have been
  installed instead archived with a tool like &Qrpm;, yielding a
  <firstterm id="D-bindist">binary distribution</firstterm>.  We could
  also partially or fully tailor a kit, bundle it up, and produce a
  <firstterm id="D-tsrcdist">tailored source distribution</firstterm>.
  It may be possible to generate more than one binary or tailored
  source distribution from a single kit, e.g., to separate the
  run-time components from development components created from a
  compiler kit.</para>

  <para>The person who is tailoring some software is a <firstterm
  id="D-tailor">tailor</firstterm> (with respect to that software).  Since
  this person will typically also compile and install the software, we
  may also call him or her the <firstterm>installer</firstterm>.  A
  person who uses software after it has been installed is an
  <firstterm id="D-enduser">end user</firstterm>.  Finally, a
  <firstterm id="D-softdev">software developer</firstterm> is a person
  who creates the software that goes into a &D-kit;.</para>

  <para>From a &D-softdev;'s perspective, a &D-kit; or &D-srcdist; is
  created from a <firstterm id="D-project">project</firstterm>.  The
  project consists of all the files in the kit that are not generated
  by &qmconfig;, as well any other files needed to support
  development, such as for version control, etc.  Some projects may
  generate more than one kit.  Projects may be composed from other
  projects.</para>

  <para>The term <firstterm id="D-package">package</firstterm> is
  often used when talking about software entitites.  We use this term
  to refer to a deliverable unit of software in any of its forms,
  whether that be a &D-kit;, a &D-srcdist;, or a &D-bindist;.  Often
  the context will clarify which form of the software is meant.</para>

 </section>

 <section id="sec-requirements-actors">
  <title>The Actors and their Use Cases</title>

  <para>We have already introduced a couple actors, the tailor and the
  software developer.  In this section, we will study these actors in
  more depth.  This will help us identify a set of use cases we must
  satisfy.</para>

  <section id="sec-requirements-actors-tailors">
   <title>Tailors</title>

   <para>As we said earlier, a &D-tailor; is an actor that customizes
   a &D-kit;.  While both &D-tailors; and &D-softdevs; are
   &D-endusers; of the &qmconfig; system, we give preference to
   meeting the needs of &D-tailors;, since while we can assume a
   &D-softdev; has some computer expertise, the same cannot be said of
   the &D-tailor;.</para>

   <para>&D-Tailors; range from the <firstterm id="D-casinst">casual
   installer</firstterm> is only interested in acquiring a handful of
   packages and probably does not want to extensively customize them,
   to the <firstterm id="D-proinst">professional systems
   administrator</firstterm>, who may need to tailor and install
   hundreds of packages, perhaps with extensive customization, perhaps
   for several different operating system platforms, perhaps repeating
   this process regularly.  A third kind of &D-tailor; is the
   <firstterm id="D-sysint">systems integrator</firstterm>,
   responsible for producing &D-bindists; and &D-tsrcdists; for
   operating system bundles or other purposes.</para>

   <section><title>&D-CasInsts-;</title>

    <para>The &D-casinst; probably wishes to know as little as
    possible about the details of tailoring.  The self-installing
    executable wizards prevalent with Windows packages, such as
    produced by &QFinstallshield;, are almost ideal for the
    &D-casinst;.  A &Qgui; is a great help, as are intelligent
    defaults, completely automated probing of the system, and (when
    possible) simple suggestions for resolving problems.  &D-Bindists;
    or &D-tsrcdists; may be preferred by &D-casinsts; over pure
    &D-srcdists;.</para>

    <para>Perhaps surprisingly to those who are not professional
    systems administrators, the system administered by &D-casinsts;
    are likely to be the most poorly maintained.  Any tool that relied
    on an accurate database of what other packages have been installed
    is likely to be inadequate for the &D-casinst;.</para>

    <para>The &D-casinst; is also going to be least equipped to create
    adequate bug reports, whether the failure be in tailoring,
    compilation, installation, or execution.  We need to be able to
    automatically report as much tailoring information as
    possible.</para>

    <para>The sort of things a &D-casinst; is likely to need to do
    are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucInstWiz"
     endterm="ucInstWiz-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucGUI"
     endterm="ucGUI-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucRepTP"
     endterm="ucRepTP-f"></xref></para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

   </section>

   <section><title>&D-ProInsts-;</title>

    <para>The &D-proinst; is likely to be someone who needs to tailor,
    build, and install hundreds of packages for many different
    platforms, sometimes without fully understanding what the package
    is supposed to do.  Often this person is using very specialized
    site conventions.  This person needs to be able to tailor software
    repeatedly with as little interaction as possible.  Being able to
    script the entire tailoring step is a major convenience.
    Conversely, a &Qgui; is a major hindrance, unless it can help
    with scripting.  Great flexibility is needed; the &D-proinst; may
    need to override defaults and probe results.  Useful documentation
    for &qmconfig; is essential.</para>

    <para>The &D-proinst; will appreciate a flexible scheme for
    specifying common site conventions.  Since site conventions may be
    complicated, extension modules (needed at tailoring time) might be
    needed.  Since many packages are being customized and built, it
    would be useful if there were a way to build and maintain a
    system-wide cache of &qmconfig; probe results.</para>

    <para>If parallel computing facilities<footnote><para>We are using
    the term loosely here to describe both true multiprocessing
    parallel systems and loosely-coupled clusters of very similar
    systems.</para></footnote> are available, then we will want to be
    able to exploit this parallelism for both conducting system probes
    and building the system.  We may need to be able to specify what
    hosts are available, and how remote commands can be started.
    These conventions may be complicated, and extension modules might
    be needed to fully exploit parallelism.</para>

    <para>The &Qautoconf; tool supports a mechanism using the
    <envar>VPATH</envar> variable, common to <command>make</command>,
    to allow one to tailor and build a package in a directory tree
    other than where the source code is located.  This makes it easy
    to build a package for several different platforms at the same
    time, a feature very useful to the &D-proinst;.  We want to
    support this feature in &qmconfig;.</para>

    <para>A &D-proinst; is likely to be someone who will need to debug
    any problems encountered during tailoring.  A common sort of
    failure is likely to be a feature probe that gave an erroneous
    result.  (Well, hopefully not too common!)  The &D-proinst; will
    want to simply "repair" the result of that test and
    re-tailor.</para>

    <para>So we can identify a few needs of the &D-proinst;, in
    addition to those of the &D-casinst;:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucInstQMCPre"
     endterm="ucInstQMCPre-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucInstQMC"
     endterm="ucInstQMC-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucUpdtQMC"
     endterm="ucUpdtQMC-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucUpdtQMCComp"
     endterm="ucUpdtQMCComp-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucUpdtPC"
     endterm="ucUpdtPC-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucScript"
     endterm="ucScript-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucCfgSite"
     endterm="ucCfgSite-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucCfgPara"
     endterm="ucCfgPara-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucCfgOver"
     endterm="ucCfgOver-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucInstTest"
     endterm="ucInstTest-f"></xref></para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

   </section>


   <section><title>&D-SysInts-;</title>

    <para>A &D-sysint; is a &D-tailor; who builds &D-bindists; that
    can be easily installed by a &D-casinst;.  These may go into a
    binary collection of software, such as one of the many &QFlinux;
    distributions.  A &D-sysint; may also prepare &D-tsrcdists; for an
    organization.</para>

    <para>In addition to the needs of &D-proinsts;, a &D-sysint; has
    these additional requirements:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucPartial"
     endterm="ucPartial-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucCreBinDist"
     endterm="ucCreBinDist-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucCfgXPlat"
     endterm="ucCfgXPlat-f"></xref></para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

   </section>

  </section>

  <section><title>&D-SoftDevs-;</title>

   <para>As we said earlier, a &D-softdev; is an actor who creates a
   &D-srcdist;.  We assume they are wise enough to use &qmconfig;.
   There are a number of different kinds of &D-softdevs;, each with
   slightly different needs.</para>

   <para>One sort of developer is the generic <firstterm
   id="D-packdev">package developer</firstterm>, an actor creating an
   arbitrary package tailored with &qmconfig;.  A special sort of
   &D-packdev; is the <firstterm id="D-qmcdev">qmconfig
   developer</firstterm>.</para>


   <section><title>&D-PackDevs-;</title>

    <para>A &D-packdev; is generally interested in creating a
    particular application.  This actor may not be expert in the
    details of software portability or large-scale systems
    administration; the actor's focus may be on a particular problem
    domain.  But we necessarily require the &D-packdev; to accommodate
    the requirements of &qmconfig;, which must not be too burdensome.
    We can facilitate compliance by providing mechanisms that will
    both simplify the software development task and guarantee
    compliance.</para>

    <para>The &D-packdev; may discover that platform-specific compiler
    bugs require special options with certain source files.  We need a
    way to express this sort of information.  (The &D-tailor; will
    also need to be able to specify exceptions, and override internal
    exceptions.  Locating these execeptions easily will be
    important.)</para>

    <para>The &D-packdev; needs to be able to produce &D-srcdists; of
    all or part of the project.  It is important that timestamps on
    archived files be sane.  There may be some changes to source files
    that should be done when the source distribution is built, like
    inserting copyrights, licenses, etc.</para>

    <para>We need to be able to interface with version control
    systems.  This may require extension modules.</para>

    <itemizedlist>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucMakeFiles"
     endterm="ucMakeFiles-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucCreProj"
     endterm="ucCreProj-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucAddProbe"
     endterm="ucAddProbe-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucTestProbe"
     endterm="ucTestProbe-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucCreKit"
     endterm="ucCreKit-f"></xref></para></listitem>

     <listitem><para><xref linkend="ucCreSrc"
     endterm="ucCreSrc-f"></xref></para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

   </section>

   <section><title>&D-QmcDevs-;</title>

    <para>A &D-qmcdev; is involved in creating or maintaining
    &qmconfig;.  All the use cases of other &D-softdevs; apply, as
    well as these additional cases:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

     <listitem><para>Update &qmconfig; Probe
     Documentation</para></listitem>

     <listitem><para>Test Probe Collection</para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

   </section>

  </section>

  <section><title>Use Cases</title>

   <para>We will now discuss the use cases we have developed for
   &qmconfig;.  Our design will try to satisfy these use cases.  This
   list tries to be broad, but is undoubtedly incomplete.</para>

   <section><title>Maintaining &qmconfig; Software</title>


    <figure id="fig-uc-maint" float="1">
     <title>&qmconfig; Maintenance Use Cases</title>
     <mediaobject>

      <imageobject>
       <imagedata align="center" width="6in" scale="50" scalefit="1"
                  fileref="uc_maint.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>

      <textobject>
       <phrase>&qmconfig; maintainance use cases</phrase>
      </textobject>

     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Several use cases are concerned with installing and
    maintaining the &qmconfig; software and its configuration on a
    system.  Since &qmconfig; has prerequisites, these also must be
    considered.  <xref linkend="fig-uc-maint"></xref> shows the
    relationships between these use cases.</para>

    <anchor id="ucInstQMCPre"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucInstQMCPre-f">UC1: Install &qmconfig;
     Prerequisite</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucInstQMCPre-a">UC1</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>

      <listitem>
       <para>It must be possible to tailor and install prerequisites
       to &qmconfig;, such as &Qpython;, on systems.</para>
      </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Essential</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>

       <para>This is probably the most difficult use case of all.
       Assuming the developers of &Qpython;, and its prerequisites
       like &Qtcl;, all adopt &qmconfig; as their customization
       system, how do we then initially tailor these packages on a
       system on which &qmconfig; has not yet been installed?  We
       cannot simply install &qmconfig;, since it needs these
       prerequisites!  We call this difficulty the
       <firstterm>bootstrap problem</firstterm>.</para>

       <para>One possible solution is to insist that all &qmconfig;
       prerequisites will already be installed, or easily available as
       &D-bindists;.  For common platforms, this may be true.  But it
       will not be true for older or less common systems, such as
       legacy &Qunix;.</para>

       <para>Another possible solution is to require these
       prerequisite packages be cross-tailored, using a different
       system.  But this is inconvenient, and requires the extensive
       knowledge of the target platform that &qmconfig; is supposed to
       replace.</para>

       <para>The &Qautoconf; tool is successful because the Bourne
       shell scripts it generates are portable to most &Qunix;
       systems.  These scripts can even be run on &Qwindows; systems,
       using a &Qunix;-compatibility tool like &QFcygwin;.  The
       drawback to using a &Qunix;-compatibility tool is that, if we
       are not careful, it can lead to run-time dependencies on this
       tool in our tailored software.  Sadly, the native batch
       language on &Qwindows; is simply not rich enough to support the
       customization process, so obvious solution of producing both a
       Bourne shell and a batch script is not an
       option.<footnote><para>If there is a good way to run scripts on
       native &Qwindows;, I would love to hear about it.  Neither I
       nor my associates are familiar with any such
       features.</para></footnote></para>

       <para>Our solution is to provide an extendible mechanism for
       building boot-strap scripts.  Initially, we will provide the
       mechanism necessary build Bourne shell boot-strap
       scripts.</para>

       <para>We emphasize that using boot-strap scripts is a very
       specialized use case.  For the near future, we expect most
       &qmconfig; users will be running on either &Qwindows; or
       &Qlinux;, for which all of &qmconfig;'s prerequisites will
       already be available in binary form.  Users of legacy &Qunix;
       systems generally will either be professional installers, or
       will have the services of a professional installer
       available.</para>

       <para>How important is this use case?  Guido van Rossum,
       Technical Director of the Python Consortium, wrote:</para>

       <blockquote><attribution><ulink
       url="http://www.software-carpentry.com/sc_config/">Guido van
       Rossum</ulink></attribution>

        <para>Nine years ago, when I first released Python to the
        world, I distributed it with a Makefile for BSD Unix. The most
        frequent questions and suggestions I received in response to
        these early distributions were about building it on different
        Unix platforms. Someone pointed me to &Qautoconf;, which
        allowed me to create a configure script that figured out
        platform idiosyncracies Unfortunately, &Qautoconf; is painful
        to use &mdash; its grouping, quoting and commenting
        conventions don't match those of the target language, which
        makes scripts hard to write and even harder to debug. I hope
        that this competition comes up with a better solution &mdash;
        it would make porting Python to new platforms a lot
        easier!</para>
       </blockquote>

       <para>Meeting this use case has a number of consequences.
       First, we must be able to interoperate with a variety of build
       systems; &qmbuild; may also be unavailable when &Qpython; and
       its prerequisites are first tailored and compiled.  Second, we
       will not be able to specify probes using any scripting
       language, since we cannot count on any particular scripting
       language being available.  This is disappointing, since it
       would be nice to use &Qpython; for this purpose.</para>

      </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Sequence</term>

      <listitem><procedure>

        <step><para>Unpack &D-srcdist; into a &D-kit;.</para></step>

        <step><para>Execute a bootstrap script with the
        <quote>help</quote> option.</para></step>

        <step><para>Determine options that need to be customized.  If
        there are many, it may be desirable to create an
        <quote>options file</quote>.</para></step>

        <step><para>Execute the bootstrap script, either with options
        or specifying the options file.</para></step>

        <step><para>Use the build system to build and install the
        package.</para></step>

       </procedure> </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucInstQMC"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucInstQMC-f">UC2: Install &qmconfig;</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucInstQMC-a">UC2</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>

      <listitem>
       <para>There must be a way to tailor and install &qmconfig; on a
       system.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>

      <listitem>
       <para>Essential</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>

      <listitem>
       <para>This is a specialized case of installing a &qmconfig;
       prerequisite.  Some help may be needed to locate &Qpython; and
       other &qmconfig; prerequisites, but since a &qmconfig; D-kit;
       contains the &qmconfig; system code, it should be possible to
       use this code to control tailoring and installation.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Sequence</term>

      <listitem><procedure>

        <step><para>Unpack &qmconfig; &D-srcdist; into a
        &D-kit;.</para></step>

        <step><para>Execute the installer script using &Qpython;,
        passing any options needed to tailor the local
        installation.</para></step>

        <step><para>Create any extension modules needed for site
        conventions.</para></step>

        <step><para>Enjoy!</para></step>
       </procedure>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucUpdtQMC"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucUpdtQMC-f">UC3: Update &qmconfig;</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucUpdtQMC-a">UC3</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>

      <listitem><para>There must be a way to update a &qmconfig;
      installation on a system.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>

      <listitem><para>Desirable</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>

      <listitem>
       <para>We would like a way to update a &qmconfig; installation
       in a convenient manner, perhaps from a central web site.</para>

       <para>Since one should be able to use &Qrpm; or other
       mechanisms to reinstall &qmconfig;, we will defer consideration
       of this use case.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucUpdtQMCComp"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucUpdtQMCComp-f">UC4: Update &qmconfig;
     Components</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucUpdtQMCComp-a">UC4</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>

      <listitem>
       <para>It is desirable to be able to update components of
       &qmconfig;, such as probes.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

      <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>

      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

      <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>

      <listitem>
       <para>&qmconfig; has many components.  We expect the collection
       of operating system feature probes to be expanding and
       improving rapidly, especially at first.  It should be possible
       to update the collection of probes from a central repository,
       without completely updating or reinstalling &qmconfig;.</para>

       <para>We expect early versions of &qmconfig; to directions on
       how to update probes.  Later versions will look towards better
       methods of updating probes, perhaps using an &QF-LDAP; database
       of available probes.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucUpdtPC"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucUpdtPC-f">UC5: Update &qmconfig; Probe Cache</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucUpdtPC-a">UC5</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>&qmconfig; can maintain a cache of probe results on a
       system.  This cache should be updated whenever operating system
       components are changed.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Inspired by &Qautoconf;, &qmconfig; supports a cache of
       probe results.  But changes to the operating system,
       application software, etc. can invalidate this cache without
       detection.  It must be possible to regenerate this
       cache.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Sequence</term>

      <listitem><procedure>

        <step>
         <para>Start &qmconfig; tool, invoking the <quote>regenerate
         probe database</quote> command.</para></step>

        <step>
         <para>Wait until it finishes.  Report any
         problems.</para></step>

       </procedure> </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

   </section>

   <section><title>Tailoring &D-SrcDists-;</title>

    <figure id="fig-uc-tailor" float="1">
     <title>&qmconfig; Tailoring Use Cases</title>
     <mediaobject>

      <imageobject>
       <imagedata align="center" width="6in" scale="50" scalefit="1"
                  fileref="uc_tailor.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>

      <textobject>
       <phrase>&qmconfig tailoring use cases</phrase>
      </textobject>

     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The main goal of &qmconfig; is to facilitate software
    tailoring, so we have use cases relating to the tailoring process.
    <xref linkend="fig-uc-tailor"></xref> shows the relationships
    between several of these use cases.  A few additional use cases
    are listed below.</para>

    <anchor id="ucInstWiz"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucInstWiz-f">UC6: Install with Wizard</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucInstWiz-a">UC6</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>For &D-casinsts;, it is ideal to be able to install a
       package in one fell swoop, without any interaction beyond what
       is truly necessary (such as to enter a user or organization
       name).</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>We expect to satisfy this use case as we continue
       developing &qmconfig;.  Ideally, it would be wonderful if any
       missing packages could also be obtained.  <xref
       linkend="instwiz"></xref> gives a detailed scenario of how the
       wizard should work.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucGUI"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucGUI-f">UC7: GUI-controlled Tailoring</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucGUI-a">UC7</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Control tailoring through a &Qgui;.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>This use case generalizes <xref linkend="ucInstWiz"
       endterm="ucInstWiz-a"></xref>.  Complete control of
       customization options is available from the &Qgui;, including
       overriding probe results.  However, while we do not want to
       hinder the &D-proinst;, we do not wish to confuse or overwhelm
       the &D-casinst; either.  So we arrange for the options that
       will be most useful to casual users to be the most easily
       accessible.  Help text will be available.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucScript"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucScript-f">UC8: Script-controlled Tailoring</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucScript-a">UC8</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Support tailoring through a command line
       interface.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Essential</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>A &D-proinst; needs to be able to completely control the
       tailoring process.  &qmconfig; can be run from the command
       line.  Tailoring can be controlled either through command line
       options or a configuration file.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucPartial"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucPartial-f">UC9: Partial Tailoring</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucPartial-a">UC9</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Allow some, but not all, aspects of tailoring to be
       completed.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Desirable</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>To create a &D-tsrcdist;, it is necessary to partially
       (but not fully) tailor a &D-kit;.  This use case is not yet
       fully developed.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucCfgSite"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucCfgSite-f">UC10: Configure &qmconfig; for Site
     Conventions</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucCfgSite-a">UC10</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>We need to be able to configure site conventions into
       &qmconfig;, so they do not need to be specified each time a
       package is tailored.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Site conventions can be either simple or complex.
       Implementation of complex conventions may require programming.
       So we should have an interface to extension modules.  This
       interface would not be usable to bootstrap scripts.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucCfgPara"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucCfgPara-f">UC11: Configure &qmconfig; for
     Parallelism</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucCfgPara-a">UC11</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Set up &qmconfig; to support parallel probing.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Desirable</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Probing can take a very long time.  While some probes
       have dependencies on the results of earlier probes, others do
       not.  We would like to be able to exploit parallelism to run
       several probes simultaneously.  It might also be possible to
       exploit this parallelism while building a &D-kit;.</para>

       <para>Depending on the system, it might be reasonable to run
       several probes at once.  This is most likely to be the case on
       SMP system.  In many environments, another option is to
       remotely execute probes on a different but identical
       machine.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucCfgOver"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucCfgOver-f">UC12: Configure Overrides</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucCfgOver-a">UC12</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Configure overrides to the results of probes.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Essential</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Sometimes probes will give unexpected results on uncommon
       or new platforms.  If tailoring is to be successful, it will be
       necessary to override some probe results.</para>

       <para>&qmconfig; must provide a mechanism to determine what
       probes will be executed to tailor a package.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <!-- Another figure here? -->

    <anchor id="ucInstTest"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucInstTest-f">UC13: Install Package for
     Testing</title>
     <titleabbrev>UC13</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>A &D-proinst; frequently needs to be able to install a
       package in a temporary <quote>test</quote> configuration,
       without disrupting a <quote>production</quote> version of the
       package.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Essential</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>New releases of software often have bugs or
       incompatibilities with other interrelated software that are not
       known until the software is installed and used.  When that
       software is mission-critical, it is essential that it can be
       installed in some sort of <quote>test</quote>
       configuration.</para>

       <para>This can be accomplished with &qmconfig; by installing
       the package into a separate directory tree.  It may be
       necessary to install other packages into this tree, too.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucCreBinDist"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucCreBinDist-f">UC14: Create a Binary
     Distribution</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucCreBinDist-a">UC14</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>A &D-sysint; may wish to create one or more &D-bindists;
       from a &D-kit;.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Desirable</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>We think that the developer of a package is best able to
       determine how it can be divided into separate binary packages.
       This avoids the problem of forgetting necessary programs or
       data files.  However, it is the &D-sysint; who actually creates
       the &D-bindists;, and we need to pass on information from the
       &D-softdev;.  Furthermore, what actually goes into a
       &D-bindist; may depend on how the &D-kit; was tailored.</para>

       <para>While creating &D-bindists; goes beyond the scope of the
       most tailoring tools, we think &qmconfig; must at least
       cooperate in this activity.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucCfgXPlat"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucCfgXPlat-f">UC15: Configure Cross-platform
     Tailoring</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucCfgXPlat-a">UC15</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Use &qmconfig; to tailor software on one platform to
       operate on another.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Desirable</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Sometimes cross-development tools are available to allow
       software to be built on one platform that will run on another
       (perhaps lacking a development environment).  Normal tailoring,
       however, will tailor for the platform on which
       cross-development is taking place, not the target.  There is a
       need to be able to tailor for different platforms.</para>

       <para>Since &qmconfig; allows the results of every probe to be
       overwritten, one way to accomplish this is to create a separate
       cache of probe results, to be used only for cross-tailoring.
       This will not help if a &D-kit; includes its own probes, so
       additional support will be needed to detect this case.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

   </section>

   <section><title>Software Development</title>

    <figure id="fig-uc-softdev" float="1">
     <title>Software Developer Use Cases</title>
     <mediaobject>

      <imageobject>
       <imagedata align="center" width="6in" scale="50" scalefit="1"
                  fileref="uc_softdev.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>

      <textobject>
       <phrase>Software developer use cases</phrase>
      </textobject>

     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><xref linkend="fig-uc-softdev"></xref> shows some of the use
    cases involved with developing software to work with &qmconfig;.
    These are discussed below.</para>


    <anchor id="ucMakeFiles"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucMakeFiles-f">UC16: Make Tailorable Source
     Files</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucMakeFiles-a">UC16</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Source files must be constructed to support
       tailoring.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Essential</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Source code that is going to be adapted by the tailoring
       process needs to be written to react to tailoring.  This is
       done by parameterizing the code on symbols or macros.  In some
       cases, templates are written, with symbols indicated; at
       customization time, these templates will be transformed into
       the real files.  In other cases, such as with C, a header file
       will be created with macro definitions in it corresponding to
       the results of feature probes.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Sequence</term>
      <listitem>
       <procedure>
        <step><para>Determine what operating system features need to
        be probed.  The &qmconfig; probe documentation will provide a
        wealth of information on operating system
        features.</para></step>

        <step><para>Determine which macros or symbols indicate results
        of testing for this feature.  The &qmconfig; probe
        documentation can provide this information.</para></step>

        <step><para>Determine optional package features, and the
        associated macro or symbol names.</para></step>

        <step><para>Modify the source code to be parameterize on these
        symbols or macros.  Make sure there are no occurrences of
        symbols or macros that may misleadingly indicate a feature
        probe result.</para></step>

        <step><para>Modify the package description database to contain
        information about the optional package feature.  Note that
        there is no need to directly include information about
        operating system probes.</para></step>

        <step><para>Make sure every source file appears in the package
        description database.</para></step>

       </procedure>
      </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucCreProj"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucCreProj-f">UC17: Create or Modify Package
     Description</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucCreProj-a">UC17</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Create or modify the &M-PDD; file.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Essential</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>&qmconfig; depends on a database to describe the project.
       This database is distributed in one or more files.  For large
       projects, it may become important to have tools to navigate
       this database.  However, in the early stages of &qmconfig;, we
       will expect these files to be created by the &D-softdev;,
       perhaps using a text editor.</para>

       <para>It has been suggested that for very large projects, a
       database service like &Q-LDAP; would be preferable to a
       file-based database like &QF-XML;.  Using &Q-LDAP; would allow
       projects to be distributed over multiple sites.  We expect to
       look more into the possibilities of distributed projects in the
       future.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucAddProbe"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucAddProbe-f">UC18: Add a Probe</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucAddProbe-a">UC18</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Some packages require special probes.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>When a package requires an operating system feature test
       not contained in the &qmconfig; probe collection, it needs to
       be added to the project.  One or more directories containing
       special probes can be added to the &M-PDD;.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucTestProbe"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucTestProbe-f">UC19: Test a Probe</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucTestProbe-a">UC19</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Test how a probe works.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>If a probe is added to a &D-kit;, there must be a way to
       test it.  (This is one of the shortcomings of &Qautoconf;.)  We
       need to be able to quickly test any &qmconfig; probe.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucIntegrate"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucIntegrate-f">UC20: Integrate Legacy Packages</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucIntegrate-a">UC20</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Integrate a package that does not use &qmconfig; into a
       package that does.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Desirable</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>&qmconfig; probes can search for installed packages, but
       sometimes there is a need to incorporate an old package
       directly into a new package.  For instance, sometime encumbered
       code cannot legally be modified, even though it is freely
       obtainable, and is only useful in conjunction with another
       package.  We need a way to be able to adapt that other
       package's build system into &qmconfig;'s.</para>

       <para>This is a difficult problem, and we do not have a
       solution yet.</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


   </section>

   <section><title>Creating &D-Kits-; and &D-SrcDists-;</title>

    <figure id="fig-uc-kit" float="1">
     <title>&qmconfig; Source Distribution Creation</title>
     <mediaobject>

      <imageobject>
       <imagedata align="center" width="6in" scale="50" scalefit="1"
                  fileref="uc_kit.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>

      <textobject>
       <phrase>&qmconfig; Source Distribution Creation</phrase>
      </textobject>

     </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>A &D-softdev; needs to create the &D-srcdists; needed by
    &D-tailors;.  <xref linkend="fig-uc-kit"></xref> shows the
    relationships between these use cases.</para>

    <anchor id="ucCreKit"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucCreKit-f">UC21: Create Kit</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucCreKit-a">UC21</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Create a &D-kit; for a project.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Essential</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Prior to creating a &D-srcdist;, all the components of a
       &D-kit; must be ready.  This use case allows &qmconfig; to use
       the build system to create any files that must be distributed
       with a &D-srcdist;.  (For instance, some files may be generated
       by special tools that are not necessarily available to
       recipients of a &D-srcdist;.)</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


    <anchor id="ucCreSrc"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucCreSrc-f">UC22: Create Source Distribution</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucCreSrc-a">UC22</titleabbrev>

     <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Create a &D-srcdist; for a project.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>The &M-PDD; contains information about what should go
       into the &D-kit; and the &D-srcdists;.  &qmconfig; can be used
       to create the actual distribution.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

   </section>

   <section><title>Problem Reporting</title>

    <para>Problems may be encountered as &qmconfig; is developed and
    new platforms (with new features and bugs) are introduced.
    &qmconfig; needs a problem reporting mechanism.</para>


    <anchor id="ucRepTP"></anchor><variablelist>

     <title id="ucRepTP-f">UC23: Report Tailoring Problem</title>
     <titleabbrev id="ucRepTP-a">UC23</titleabbrev>

    <varlistentry><term>Description</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Report problems with the tailoring process.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Priority</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Important</para> </listitem></varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Discussion</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>If tailoring fails, e.g., a probe gives a completely
       unexpected result, then a problem report needs to be sent.  It
       probably should go to the maintainer of the package, who can
       then forward it to the &qmconfig; development team.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

   </section>

  </section>

 </section>

</chapter>

<!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: sgml
  indent-tabs-mode: nil
  sgml-indent-step: 1 
  sgml-always-quote-attributes: t
  sgml-general-insert-case: lower
  sgml-minimize-attributes: nil
  sgml-parent-document: ("qmconfig.xml" "book" "chapter")
  End:
-->
