<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

  File:   track-tour.xml
  Author: Alex Samuel
  Date:   2001-08-02

  Contents:
    Grand tour/tutorial of QMTrack.

  Copyright (C) 2001 CodeSourcery LLC.  This material may
  be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions set forth in
  the Software Carpentry Open Publication License, which is available at:

    http://www.software-carpentry.com/openpub-license.html

-->
<chapter id="chap-track-tour">
 <title>Getting Started with &qmtrack;</title>
 
 <para>This chapter will help you get &qmtrack; up and running by
 showing you how to create and configure an issue database, and perform
 basic operations.</para>

 <para>The sections on issue database configuration are primarily of
 interest to administrators and maintiners; users can skip directly to
 ... to learn how to work with issues in &qmtrack;.</para>

 <section id="sec-tracktut-idb">
  <title>Creating an &idb;</title>

  <para>&qmtrack; stores information about bugs and other issues in an
  issue database (&idb;).  Before you begin using &qmtrack;, you must
  instruct it to create and initialize a new &idb;.</para>

  <para>To initialize an empty &idb;, invoke:</para>

  <screen>
&prompt;<userinput>qmtrack initialize <replaceable>path</replaceable></userinput> 
  </screen>

  <para>&qmtrack; creates a new &idb; at the
  <replaceable>path</replaceable> you specified, and prints some
  explanatory information.  The &idb; is a directory containing various
  files that &qmtrack; uses to store configuration information and the
  issues themselves.</para>

  <para>Once you've initialized a new &idb;, you must let &qmtrack; know
  where it is.  To do this, either set the environment variable
  <envar>QMTEST_IDB_PATH</envar> to the &idb; path, or specify the
  <option>&dashdash;idb</option> (<option>-D</option>) option when you
  invoke the &qmtrack-cmd; command.</para>

 </section> <!-- sec-tracktut-idb -->

 <section id="sec-tracktut-user-db">
  <title>Configuring Users</title>

  <para>When &qmtrack; created the new &idb;, it included a user
  database file.  This file specifies information about the &qmtrack;'s
  user accounts, since &qmtrack; doesn't automatically use the user
  accounts on your system.  The default user database contains a single
  user account named "guest", which is the default account that it used
  when accessing &qmtrack; through its Web user interface.</para>

  <para>To create additional user accounts, you must modify the user
  database file by hand.  The database file is named
  <filename>users.xml</filename>, and is in the directory that &qmtrack;
  made at the &idb; path you specified.  The user database file is an
  XML file.</para>

  <para>To create a new user, add a paragraph similar to this
  one:</para>

   <programlisting>
<![CDATA[ <user id="johndoe" disabled="no">
  <info>
   <property name="name">John Doe</property>
   <property name="email">john@doe.org</property>
  </info>
  <authentication>
   <property name="password">!h@rd2guesSs</property>
  </authentication>
 </user>
]]></programlisting>

  <para>You should also add at least one user to the "administrators"
  group.  Only users in this group are allowed to change the &idb;
  configuration.  To add a user to the "administrators" group, add a
  line to the administrators <sgmltag class="element">group</sgmltag>
  element, so that it looks similar to this:</para>

  <programlisting>
<![CDATA[ <group id="administrators">
  <user-id>johndoe</user-id>
 </group>
]]></programlisting>

  <para>Specify a user ID of one of the users in your user database
  instead of "johndoe".  You may add more than one user to the
  "administrators" group, if you wish.</para>

  <para>See <xref linkend="sec-user-database"/> for more information
  about the user database.</para>

 </section> <!-- sec-tracktut-user-db -->

 <section id="sec-tracktut-server">
  <title>Starting the Server</title>

  <para>&qmtrack; provides a Web-based user interface and remote access
  capabilities through a built-in Web server.  While &qmtrack; does
  support a command-line interface, you can perform most tasks,
  including configuration, from the Web interface.</para>

  <para>To start the server, use the <command>qmtrack server</command>
  command.  Specify the TCP port number on which to run the server with
  the <option>&dashdash;port</option> (<option>-P</option>) option.
  Don't forget to specify the path to the &idb;.</para>

  <para>For example, if you created an &idb; at the path
  <filename>~/idb</filename>, run the &qmtrack; server on port 8000 by
  invoking:</para>

  <screen>
&prompt;<userinput>export QMTRACK_IDB_PATH=~/idb</userinput>
&prompt;<userinput>qmtrack server -P 8000</userinput>
  </screen>

  <para>Once the server is running, you may access the &qmtrack; Web
  user interface by pointing your browser at this URL:</para>

  <programlisting>
   http://<replaceable>hostname</replaceable>:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/track/
  </programlisting>

  <para>Replace <replaceable>hostname</replaceable> with the host name
  of your computer, and <replaceable>port</replaceable> with the port
  number you specified.</para>

 </section> <!-- sec-tracktut-server -->

 <section id="sec-tracktut-issue-class">
  <title>Creating an Issue Class</title>

  <para>You must perform one additional step before using &qmtrack; to
  track bugs and issues.  To use an &idb;, you must create an issue
  class, which specifies the information stored for each issue.  An
  issue class is like a blank form that includes preprinted fields.
  When you create or modify an issue, you specify the values for these
  fields.</para>

  <para>&qmtrack; allows you to use more than one issue class in your
  &idb;.  However, for simple cases, one issue class is generally
  sufficient.  If later you find you need more than one, simply repeat
  the steps here to create additional issue classes.</para>

  <para>To create an issue class, you must log in to the &qmtrack; Web
  interface with a user account in the "administrators" group.  Enter
  the user name and password on the left side of the main &qmtrack;
  page, and click on the <guibutton>Log In</guibutton> button.  If you
  configured your user database correctly, the main &qmtrack; page
  should now include a category labelled
  <guilabel>Administrative</guilabel> in the bottom right, including a
  <guibutton>Configure IDB...</guibutton> button.  Click on this button
  to start configuring your &idb;</para>

  <para>From the <guilabel>Configure Issue Database</guilabel> page,
  select the <guibutton>Add a New Class...</guibutton> button.  Enter a
  name and title for your issue class.  The name is used internally by
  &qmtrack;, while the title will be visible to users.  Both may be the
  same.  For example, specify "bug" for both.  The
  <guilabel>Categories</guilabel> control allows you to specify a list
  of names for categorizing your issues.  A category is simply a
  non-exclusive set of issues; i.e. an issue may belong to zero, one, or
  more categoires.  If you're happy with the default category names
  provided by &qmtrack;, simply leave them.  When you're all done, click
  on the <guibutton>Create</guibutton> button.</para>

  <para>&qmtrack; returns you to the <guilabel>Configure Issue
  Database</guilabel> page, which now shows your new issue class.  Click
  on its <guibutton>Edit...</guibutton> button to examine its details.
  You'll notice that &qmtrack; has included a several fields
  automatically; these fields are included in all issue classes, and
  cannot be deleted.  From this page, you can add additional fields,
  modify the settings of existing fields, and configure other special
  features.  When you're done, be sure to click on the <guibutton>Commit
  Changes</guibutton> button at the bottom of the form; &qmtrack; does
  not change the issue in the &idb; until you do this.</para>

  <para>When you are done editing your issue class, click on the
  <guilabel>Main Page</guilabel> link on the title bar at the top of the
  page to return to the main page.</para>

 </section> <!-- sec-tracktut-issue-class -->

</chapter>
<!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: sgml
  indent-tabs-mode: nil
  sgml-indent-step: 1 
  sgml-always-quote-attributes: t
  sgml-general-insert-case: lower
  sgml-minimize-attributes: nil
  sgml-parent-document: ("manual.xml" "book" "chapter")
  End:
-->
