<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

  File:   track-manual.xml
  Author: Alex Samuel
  Date:   2001-05-25

  Contents:
    Manual for QMTrack.

  Copyright (C) 2001 CodeSourcery LLC.  This material may
  be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions set forth in
  the Software Carpentry Open Publication License, which is available at:

    http://www.software-carpentry.com/openpub-license.html

-->
<chapter id="chap-track-manual">
 <title>Using &qmtrack;</title>
 
 <section id="sec-qmtrack-concepts">
  <title>&qmtrack; Concepts</title>

  <para>This section describes the basic concepts of &qmtrack;.</para>

  <section id="sec-issues">
   <title>Issues</title>

   <para>An <firstterm>issue</firstterm> is the fundamental record of
   information in &qmtrack;.  An issue represents a single bug,
   problem report, enhancement request, etc. stored in &qmtrack;'s
   database.</para>

   <para>An issue is usually represented in &qmtrack;'s user
   interfaces as a form.  The form is made of fields, and the issue
   has a value for each field.  The value may, for some fields, be
   empty.  Like the blanks of a preprinted form, the fields in an
   issue define a standard set of information that is provided for
   each issue.</para>

  </section> <!-- sec-issues -->

  <section id="sec-issue-ids">
   <title>Issue IDs</title>

   <para>Each issue is represented by a unique <firstterm>issue
   ID</firstterm>, or <firstterm>IID</firstterm>.  The issue ID is a
   tag composed of lower case letters, digits, and underscores.</para>

   <para>When you create a new issue, you may choose any issue ID you
   wish, unless another issue already exists with the same issue ID in
   the issue database, or unless the issue database has been
   configured to assign issue IDs automatically.  Try to choose an
   issue ID that is short, and that is reminiscent of the just of the
   issue.</para>

  </section> <!-- sec-issue-ids -->

  <section id="sec-issue-classes">
   <title>Issue Classes</title>

   <para>Not all issues need have the same fields.  An
   <firstterm>issue classes</firstterm> defines a schema of fields
   that may be used for an issue.  Each issue belongs to a single
   issue class, which defines the fields that are present in the
   issue.  Issue classes are configured as part of the &qmtrack;
   database.</para>

   <para>When you create a new issue, you must choose one of the
   available issue classes for the new issue.  Once an issue has been
   created, its issue class cannot be changed.</para>

  </section> <!-- sec-issue-classes -->

  <section id="sec-revisions">
   <title>Revisions</title>

   <para>An issue is typically modified over the course of its
   lifetime.  For example, as a bug is analyzed and subsequently
   fixed, information and annotations are added to the bug report, and
   finally the bug is closed.</para>

   <para>When you change an issue, &qmtrack; does not simply discard
   the old version.  In fact, &qmtrack; preserves all the versions of
   each issue since its creation.  These versions are called
   <firstterm>revisions</firstterm>.  This allows you to view an
   issue's complete revision history.</para>

   <para>Revisions are numbered sequentially, starting with zero for
   an issue's initial revision.  Most users need not concern
   themselves with revision numbers, though, since they will generally
   be interested only with the highest-numbered revision of any issue,
   the <firstterm>current revision</firstterm>.</para>

  </section> <!-- sec-revisions -->

 </section> <!-- sec-qmtrack-concepts -->

</chapter> <!-- chap-track-manual -->
<!--
  Local Variables:
  mode: sgml
  indent-tabs-mode: nil
  sgml-indent-step: 1 
  sgml-always-quote-attributes: t
  sgml-general-insert-case: lower
  sgml-minimize-attributes: nil
  sgml-parent-document: ("manual.xml" "book" "chapter")
  End:
-->
